<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Blog on Aadam | DevOps Engineer</title><link>https://aadamali.net/blog/</link><description>Blog Posts by Aadam Ali</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>2023-06-18</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aadamali.net/blog/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Hello World!</title><link>https://aadamali.net/blog/hello-world/</link><pubDate>2023-06-18</pubDate><guid>https://aadamali.net/blog/hello-world/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="who-am-i">Who Am I?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Hello! My name is Aadam, at the time of writing I&amp;rsquo;m an Apprentice DevOps
Engineer working at
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/hm-revenue-customs/about">HMRC&lt;/a>,
on the &lt;a href="https://hmrc.github.io/">MDTP&lt;/a> (Multi Channel Digital Tax
Platform) for the Build and Deploy team.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve been involved with technology for the best part of the last 6
years, ever since I built my first PC (Pentium G4400, RX 480, 8GB RAM).
And thanks to the first COVID-19 lockdown I started learning full
stack web development - my first foray into programming outside of my
GSCE and A-Level Computer Science courses. Over the following months, I
learnt HTML, CSS, and JavaScript before moving on to Node.js, React,
and MongoDB, using Linux (Ubuntu via WSL) and Git along the way.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My first self-directed full stack project was
&lt;a href="https://github.com/Aadam-Ali/twitter-clone">twitter-clone&lt;/a>, which
unsurpisingly was my attempt to clone Twitter using the MERN (MongoDB,
Express, React, and Node.js) stack, if you have look at the repository
my lack of knowledge at the time really shows - I wrote all the code
without tests in two commits! I didn&amp;rsquo;t manage to finish it but I intend
to do a V2 with my new found knowledge.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Not long after writing twitter-clone, I found out that I had been
enrolled onto the apprenticeship, and so my focus shifted to learning
the tools that I knew were being used on MDTP. I now spend most of my
time working with AWS, Python, Terraform, Jenkins, and Artifactory.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-am-i-starting-a-blog">Why Am I Starting A Blog?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>There are three main reasons:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Recently, I completed my apprenticeship portfolio - the only regular
writing that I was doing. As someone who doesn&amp;rsquo;t particularly enjoy
writing I wanted a reason to keep writing regularly.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Most software / devops engineers have benefited from blog posts,
whether it was finding a solution to a very specific problem,
learning a new concept, or even gaining understanding of different
perspectives on various topics.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A blog allows me to keep a record of the projects, learnings,
experiences, and achievements I&amp;rsquo;ve made over time - it&amp;rsquo;s a window into
past versions of myself that I can look back on and reflect on how
I&amp;rsquo;ve improved.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Alongside the above points the straw that broke the camel&amp;rsquo;s back was
reading Ben Kuhn&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://www.benkuhn.net/writing/">&amp;lsquo;Why and how to write things on the
Internet&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a>. For anyone else
considering starting a blog but unsure about how to start writing, I
highly recommend reading it.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-can-you-expect">What Can You Expect?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I don&amp;rsquo;t really have a set of topics that I&amp;rsquo;m going to limit this blog
to, however, I expect that the majority of posts will cover topics, and
concepts under the DevOps umbrella: cloud, programming, cybersecurity,
etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What I can guarantee is that my next few posts will be about: the
architecture of this site, my hardware, my development environment,
and my apprenticeship experience. You can also expect new posts every
two weeks.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I also intend to add another section to the site, Snippets.
Snippets will be very short posts containing code snippets and commands
that I find useful in my daily work.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="closing">Closing&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Thank you for taking the time to read this post, hopefully, the first
of many. If you are interested in following my blog, there is an &lt;a href="https://aadamali.net/blog/rss.xml">RSS
feed&lt;/a> available. Feel free to reach out to me if you
have any suggestions for topics you&amp;rsquo;d like me to write about, or
improvements that could be made to this site.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>