<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Blog on Aadam | DevOps Engineer</title><link>https://aadamali.net/blog/</link><description>Blog Posts by Aadam Ali</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>2023-07-02</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aadamali.net/blog/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Site Design</title><link>https://aadamali.net/blog/site-design/</link><pubDate>2023-07-02</pubDate><guid>https://aadamali.net/blog/site-design/</guid><description>&lt;p>As promised in my &lt;a href="https://aadamali.net/blog/hello-world">first post&lt;/a>, here is the post
about the architecture (and design) of this site. I&amp;rsquo;m going to talk
about the tools and design choices made that made this webiste possible.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="hugo">Hugo&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>My first decision was to use a static site generator (SSG) - this was to
avoid the overhead of having to manage the HTML and CSS for each page,
allowing me to concentrate on actually writing the content. This is also
helped by the fact that in most SSGs posts are written in Markdown
rather than HTML, which makes writing content much easier.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Choosing an SSG was fairly straightforward, I wanted to use something
that was well documented and had a large community. This left me with
two choices, &lt;a href="https://gohugo.io/about/what-is-hugo/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hugo&lt;/a> and
&lt;a href="https://jekyllrb.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Jekyll&lt;/a>. I ended up choosing Hugo for two main
reasons, I liked the fact that it was a single binary and didn&amp;rsquo;t require
me to install anything extra on my system for example Jekyll requires
Ruby to be installed on your system. The second reason was that Hugo
seemed to be the faster of the two options.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>From my experience so far Hugo is pretty easy to use. I was able to set
up this website&amp;rsquo;s components (header, footer, title sections, etc.) and
layouts - single pages (like the one you&amp;rsquo;re reading) and lists, e.g.
&lt;a href="https://aadamali.net/blog">/blog&lt;/a> - within a couple of hours.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="two-repos">Two Repos&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This website is managed using two repositories, blog and
&lt;a href="https://github.com/Aadam-Ali/aadamali.net" target="_blank" rel="noopener">aadamali.net&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The blog repo contains the &lt;a href="https://gohugo.io/getting-started/directory-structure/#new-site-scaffolding" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hugo directory
structure&lt;/a>
and a &lt;code>Makefile&lt;/code> (see below):&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">archetypes/ content/ hugo.toml Makefile resources/ themes/
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">assets/ data/ layouts/ public/ static
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>This is a private repository that I do not intend on making publicly
available. However, if there is interest in the theme of this site, I am
happy to create a separate repository containing the Hugo theme.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>aadamali.net is a public repository that contains the static content
that you are currently viewing. This is a submodule of the blog
repository under the &lt;code>public/&lt;/code> directory. To build the content I run the
&lt;code>make&lt;/code> command from the blog repository, I then commit and push the
static content in &lt;code>public/&lt;/code> to GitHub - at some point I&amp;rsquo;ll automate this
using GitHub Actions.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="github-pages">GitHub Pages&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In terms of hosting I wanted to start with something cheap or free for
two main reasons. Firstly, the content on the site is static and does
not require any complex infrastructure. Secondly, I did not want to
invest into something that I had not fully developed the habit of
contributing to.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What better way to do this than to use GitHub Pages, which I enabled on
my aadamali.net repository and configured to automatically create a new
deployment on pushes to the main branch.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="design">Design&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The design is something that I wanted to be personal yet simple. That is
why I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to use one of the many community created &lt;a href="https://themes.gohugo.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hugo
themes&lt;/a> that are freely available but rather
write my own CSS.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>From my point of view there are two main components to this design, the
colour scheme and the font.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In terms of colours I decided to use the &lt;a href="https://github.com/morhetz/gruvbox#dark-mode-1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Gruvbox Dark
mode&lt;/a> palette because I
use it on my machines, mainly as my terminal colour scheme, as it is
easy on the eyes. However, this is very much subject to change as I
didn&amp;rsquo;t want to spend too much time on design, so I went with a
predefined colour palette.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/lp/mono/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">JetBrains Mono&lt;/a> is the font I have
chosen and similar to the colour scheme I use it in the terminal as well
as text editors / IDEs. I&amp;rsquo;m conflicted in this area as I don&amp;rsquo;t think the
monospace look is to everyone&amp;rsquo;s taste and am considering switching to
something like &lt;a href="https://fonts.google.com/specimen/Fira&amp;#43;Sans" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Fira Sans&lt;/a>
or &lt;a href="https://fonts.google.com/specimen/Fira&amp;#43;Sans&amp;#43;Condensed" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Fira Sans
Condensed&lt;/a> as
they&amp;rsquo;re in the same family as &lt;a href="https://fonts.google.com/specimen/Fira&amp;#43;Code" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Fira
Code&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://fonts.google.com/specimen/Fira&amp;#43;Mono" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Fira
Mono&lt;/a>, two fonts that I use
alternatively to JetBrains Mono.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="closing">Closing&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Thank you for taking the time to read this post. Please feel free to
contact me with your thoughts on the font choice, or with topics you&amp;rsquo;d
like me to write about in the future.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Hello World!</title><link>https://aadamali.net/blog/hello-world/</link><pubDate>2023-06-18</pubDate><guid>https://aadamali.net/blog/hello-world/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="who-am-i">Who Am I?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Hello! My name is Aadam, at the time of writing I&amp;rsquo;m an Apprentice DevOps
Engineer working at
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/hm-revenue-customs/about" target="_blank" rel="noopener">HMRC&lt;/a>,
on the &lt;a href="https://hmrc.github.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MDTP&lt;/a> (Multi Channel Digital Tax
Platform) for the Build and Deploy team.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve been involved with technology for the best part of the last 6
years, ever since I built my first PC (Pentium G4400, RX 480, 8GB RAM).
And thanks to the first COVID-19 lockdown I started learning full stack
web development - my first foray into programming outside of my GSCE and
A-Level Computer Science courses. Over the following months, I learnt
HTML, CSS, and JavaScript before moving on to Node.js, React, and
MongoDB, using Linux (Ubuntu via WSL) and Git along the way.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My first self-directed full stack project was
&lt;a href="https://github.com/Aadam-Ali/twitter-clone" target="_blank" rel="noopener">twitter-clone&lt;/a>, which
unsurpisingly was my attempt to clone Twitter using the MERN (MongoDB,
Express, React, and Node.js) stack, if you have look at the repository
my lack of knowledge at the time really shows - I wrote all the code
without tests in two commits! I didn&amp;rsquo;t manage to finish it but I intend
to do a V2 with my new found knowledge.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Not long after writing twitter-clone, I found out that I had been
enrolled onto the apprenticeship, and so my focus shifted to learning
the tools that I knew were being used on MDTP. I now spend most of my
time working with AWS, Python, Terraform, Jenkins, and Artifactory.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-am-i-starting-a-blog">Why Am I Starting A Blog?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>There are three main reasons:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Recently, I completed my apprenticeship portfolio - the only regular
writing that I was doing. As someone who doesn&amp;rsquo;t particularly enjoy
writing I wanted a reason to keep writing regularly.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Most software / devops engineers have benefited from blog posts,
whether it was finding a solution to a very specific problem, learning
a new concept, or even gaining understanding of different perspectives
on various topics.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A blog allows me to keep a record of the projects, learnings,
experiences, and achievements I&amp;rsquo;ve made over time - it&amp;rsquo;s a window into
past versions of myself that I can look back on and reflect on how
I&amp;rsquo;ve improved.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Alongside the above points the straw that broke the camel&amp;rsquo;s back was
reading Ben Kuhn&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://www.benkuhn.net/writing/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&amp;lsquo;Why and how to write things on the
Internet&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a>. For anyone else
considering starting a blog but unsure about how to start writing, I
highly recommend reading it.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-can-you-expect">What Can You Expect?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I don&amp;rsquo;t really have a set of topics that I&amp;rsquo;m going to limit this blog
to, however, I expect that the majority of posts will cover topics, and
concepts under the DevOps umbrella: cloud, programming, cybersecurity,
etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What I can guarantee is that my next few posts will be about: the
architecture of this site, my hardware, my development environment, and
my apprenticeship experience. You can also expect new posts every two
weeks.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I also intend to add another section to the site, Snippets. Snippets
will be very short posts containing code snippets and commands that I
find useful in my daily work.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="closing">Closing&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Thank you for taking the time to read this post, hopefully, the first of
many. If you are interested in following my blog, there is an &lt;a href="https://aadamali.net/blog/rss.xml">RSS
feed&lt;/a> available. Feel free to reach out to me if you have
any suggestions for topics you&amp;rsquo;d like me to write about, or improvements
that could be made to this site.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>